<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lars Walen</title>
    <description>I&#39;m a software engineer near Seattle who likes woodworking.
</description>
    <link>http://lars.walen.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lars.walen.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 15:19:36 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 15:19:36 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zelda Chest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I made this chest to look like the one in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_Ocarina_of_Time&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But instead of rupees or a hookshot, I use it like a file cabinet. It’s the perfect size for manila folders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/closed.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/closed_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s made out of 3/4” pine boards (stained dark), except for the banding, which is maple (spray-painted black).
The whole thing was sprayed with satin water-based polyurethane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/open.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/open_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the sides of the top was tricky. I ended up making the five sections with rougly the correct angles, and then ran the bottom part over the jointer to flatten it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/top.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/zelda-chest/top_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I wanted to replicate the look of the rivet heads on the banding, like the one in the game. Later I changed my mind, because I couldn’t think of a good way to do it, and I prefer the clean look of this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/zelda-chest</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/zelda-chest</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Coffee Tables</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;These coffee tables are based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.finewoodworking.com/woodworking-plans/article/stylish-coffee-table-with-sleek-lines.aspx&quot;&gt;plans in Fine Woodworking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/coffee-tables/tops.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/coffee-tables/tops_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made them a bit wider than the plans and used solid wood for the top, since I had a bunch of local cherry. The legs and rails are all glued up to get the right thickness, since I only have 4/4 boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/coffee-tables/legs.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/coffee-tables/legs_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my HVLP sprayer to apply 5 or 6 coats of clear, water-based polyurethane, sanding between the later coats.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/coffee-tables</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/coffee-tables</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mallet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the mallet I use when I need a little more delicacy than a hammer.
It has really nice proportions and weight, and has held up well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/mallet/actual.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/mallet/actual_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The head came from a piece of Big Leaf Maple firewood and the handle is a piece of hard maple. The head has a square tapered hole, and the handle has the same taper. The handle can only be as wide as the narrowest part of the hole, in order to fit through. The edges of the handle are chamfered a bit to make it more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drilled a few holes in the block to clear out some material, then used a chisel to make it square. It took a long time, and I hope this mallet lasts a long time so I don’t have to do it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a dimensioned drawing of this mallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/mallet/plan.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/mallet/plan_small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/mallet</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/mallet</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pencil Holder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I made this pencil holder for my mom last Christmas. It’s made from 3/8 inch
thick cherry, with mitered corners and walnut splines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/pencil-holder/far.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/pencil-holder/far_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom is a piece of quarter inch plywood, set into a rabbet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/pencil-holder/close.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/pencil-holder/close_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished it with Danish oil and paste wax.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/pencil-holder</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/pencil-holder</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Step Stool</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This stool was a Christmas present for my sister, who complains about being short a lot. It’s made of 1 inch thick cherry, with walnut dowels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/top_1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/top_1_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top is a single wide piece, but the legs are each joined up from three narrower pieces. I made sure the lighter (sapwood) edges were on the inside faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/top_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/top_2_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hole in the top was made with a router. I made a pattern of the same size out of some 3/8” plywood, used double-sided tape to stick it to the board. Then I used a flush-trimming bit to route the slot. The advantage of doing it this was is that the pattern was thinner, so it was easier to make perfect with sandpaper and files. I can also reuse it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything was just glued together with butt joints, and when that dried I drilled through both pieces and glued in dowels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/underside.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/underside_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cross-piece gives the stool most of it’s rigidity. I would be nervous about the joints I did if it weren’t for this piece keeping the sides from splaying and breaking the joints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished the stool with a coat or two of Danish oil. Then I rubbed on paste wax when that was dry. I’m not sure if this is ideal, since it feels a bit slippery. But my sister hasn’t mentioned it, so it seems to be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/plan.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/step-stool/plan_small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to build your own, or just want to see how it goes together, download &lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/files/step-stool/model.skp&quot;&gt;this SketchUp Model&lt;/a&gt; (requires SketchUp 2013 or newer, which &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sketchup.com/download&quot;&gt;you can download for free&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/step-stool</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/step-stool</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chopping Axe Sheath</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The plastic blade guard that came with my Fiskars chopping axe was even worse than the one for the splitter, probably because it is an older model. Plus, it looks dumb when I carry it around in the woods. So, as I did for my &lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/splitting-axe-sheath&quot;&gt;splitting axe&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to do for my chopping axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I didn’t take any pictures of making the sheath, because I got caught up making it. The construction is the same as on my splitting axe sheath. I do have pictures after finishing it though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/front.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/front_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/front_stitch.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/front_stitch_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/on_axe.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/on_axe_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/strap_stitching.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/strap_stitching_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/with_axe.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/with_axe_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to make your own, I have templates!
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/files/chopping-axe-sheath/plan.pdf&quot;&gt;This PDF&lt;/a&gt;
can be printed on a piece of US Letter paper (8.5’’ by 11’’), and used as a template for each of the pieces, besides the strap, which is just a rectangle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/files/chopping-axe-sheath/plan.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/chopping-axe-sheath/plan.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/chopping-axe-sheath</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/chopping-axe-sheath</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Splitting Axe Sheath</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn’t really like the plastic sheaths that came with my Fiskars axes. They were a little cumbersome to use, and definitely too bulky. So, I decided to make my own out of leather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/complete_1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/complete_1_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by making a template out of cardboard. I knew that I wanted the sheath to fold over the top of the blade, and have a seam at the sharp part. So I took a piece of cardboard, folded it over the top, and cut it to the shape I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/cardboard_1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/cardboard_1_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also put a small strip of leather up against the sharp part of the blade. This helps to ensure that the blade will not cut through the stitching, and it makes the fold at the top corner less drastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the cardboard template on, I also experimented with the size and position of the strap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/cardboard_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/cardboard_2_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was satisfied with the shape and fit of the cardboard template, I removed it, flattened it out, and placed in on a piece of leather. I held it in place while I cut the leather to the same shape and size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/flat_cutout.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/flat_cutout_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cut out a strap based on the length of the cardboard strap I had made earlier. This strap needed to be long enough to loop around the handle, and have space beyond the snap to make it easy to grab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I cut out the spacer from a scrap. The L shape of this piece helps to prevent the blade from slipping out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/spacer.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/spacer_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I folded the sheath body over the top of the blade, and clamped it along the edge that would later be sewn, with the spacer in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/clamped.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/clamped_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arranged the strap in a way that would hold the sheath firmly, and taped the back end in place with some masking tape. I removed the clamps holding the sheath together, and flattened it to make it easier to sew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/strap_taped.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/strap_taped_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I drilled holes for the stitching to hold the strap with a 1/16’’ drill bit. At first, I tried to drive the thread through with a leather awl, but found the leather too heavy for that. Eventually I bought some stitching needles to thread the string through the pre-drilled holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sewed the strap with a stitch that works like a sewing machine, so a loop of the thread is just pushed through a hole, and a thread on the other side goes through it. This worked okay, but I used a different stitch later. I finished the stitching with square knots on the inside of the sheath—nothing fancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/strap_sewn.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/strap_sewn_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then clamped the sheath back on the axe, and positioned the strap for the snap. The male end of the snap goes on the sheath itself, with the female part on the strap. I put a piece of masking tape on the sheath, on each side of the strap. I punched a hole between them using a leather punch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/snap_hole.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/snap_hole_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I removed a bit of leather from the inside of the sheath, so that the back of the snap would not protrude as much. I inserted the back of the snap…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/male_snap_1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/male_snap_1_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… then placed the front on top. Using the anvil and setter that came with my snaps, I hammered the inside of the snap over until it was firmly secured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/male_snap_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/male_snap_2_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I placed the sheath back on the axe, clamped it in place, and drilled holes for the front seam. It took some fiddling to get the spacer where I wanted it, so that it would be up against the edge of the blade. I started by drilling a hole at the top and bottom, and putting a temporary string through them so the clamps wouldn’t be in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_temp.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_temp_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I stitched up the seam. I used a two needle stitch, where each goes through each hole from the opposite side. This was a bit easier than my previous method, but I still broke a couple needles. If I had made the holes a bit larger, I wouldn’t have needed touse pliers to pull the needles through, and probably wouldn’t have broken any. But, I wanted the holes to be small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_start.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_start_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the seam, I tied the ends of the string together between the leather, and shoved them out of sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_complete.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/main_seam_complete_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I placed the sheath on the axe, looped the strap around, and held it over the male end of the snap. I tapped on the strap to make a mark on the inside where the snap was. Then I removed the sheath from the axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the inside of the strap, I measured about 1/8’’ from the center of the circle made by the snap, in the direction of the stitched end. Here I punched a hole and installed the female end of the snap. Going back 1/8’’ ensured that the strap would need to be pulled tight across the axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I considered it done. My leather did not appear to need dyeing at the edges, so I left it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/complete_2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/complete_2_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like how it turned out. The smooth black leather and the shape of the sheath fit the style of the Fiskars axe well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plans&quot;&gt;Plans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to make your own sheath, I have templates!
&lt;a href=&quot;files/splitting-axe-sheath/plan.pdf&quot;&gt;This PDF&lt;/a&gt;
can be printed on a piece of US Letter paper (8.5’’ by 11’’), and used as a template for each of the pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/files/splitting-axe-sheath/plan.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/splitting-axe-sheath/plan.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leather I used came from an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leatherunltd.com/leather/pieces/pieces.html&quot;&gt;8 oz. Smooth Black Strap Leather Bundle from Leather Unlimited&lt;/a&gt;. I bought &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandyleatherfactory.com/en-usd/home/department/tools/3631-00.aspx&quot;&gt;Easy-To-Do Line 24 Snaps &amp;amp; Setter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandyleatherfactory.com/en-usd/home/department/lacing/11210-350.aspx&quot;&gt;Waxed Braided Cord&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandyleatherfactory.com/en-usd/home/home.aspx&quot;&gt;Tandy Leather&lt;/a&gt;. The axe is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.fiskars.com/Gardening-and-Yard-Care/Products/Axes-and-Striking-Tools/Splitting-Axes/X27-Super-Splitting-Axe-36#.U6dlPXVdWV4&quot;&gt;Fiskars X27 Super Splitting Axe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/splitting-axe-sheath</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/splitting-axe-sheath</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Folding TV Stand</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I built this stand to hold my TV in my room at college. I made it foldable so that it would be compact for when I eventually returned home, and because I wanted to try to build something with moving pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_in_place.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_in_place_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stand is made of 3/4” by 3 1/2” common pine boards. First the top was made by laminating four pieces together. Then I routed and chiseled the grooves for the horizontal supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_open.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_open_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I cut boards for the horizontal supports to length. I then made the triangular stop blocks and glued them to the horizontal supports. These are also recessed into the top of the stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_folded.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/complete_folded_small.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legs are trimmed to a width that will sit flush with the horizontal supports when the stand is folded. This width is also the diameter of the half-circle at the top of the legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The length of the legs must be short enough for them to fold in without hitting the opposing dowel. The dowels rest in holes drilled either part or all the way through the horizontal supports. The cross braces on the legs are positioned to not interfere with each other when the stand is folded, and also to be at the same height when the stand is unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_open.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_open_small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_folded.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_folded_small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_bottom.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/img/folding-tv-stand/drawing_bottom_small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to build this, you may use
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lars.walen.me/files/folding-tv-stand/model.skp&quot;&gt;this SketchUp model&lt;/a&gt;,
which includes dimensions of all pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lars.walen.me/folding-tv-stand</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lars.walen.me/folding-tv-stand</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
